A Guide to the Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1802-1881 (bulk 1873)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1802-1881 (bulk 1873).
The Library of Virginia
Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1802-001-1881-001
Digital images.
Madison County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Digital images were generated by PTFS through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
Historical Information
Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
Madison County was named for James Madison, a Virginian statesman, author of the United States Constitution, and member of Congress when the county was formed from Culpeper County by a statute adopted on 4 December 1792. This was the second Virginia county to be named for future president Madison. The county court first met on 23 May 1793.
Scope and Content
Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1802-1881 (bulk 1873), are indexed into the Chancery Records Index. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, slave records, business records or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
Arrangement
Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found. Arranged chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Madison County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm.
See The Chancery Records Index to search for chancery suits of additional Virginia localities.
Additional pre-1913 Madison County (Va.) Chancery Causes that were stored at the courthouse are currently being processed and will be made available on the The Chancery Records Index once they have been digitally reformatted
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Madison County (Va.) Circuit Court
Subjects:
African Americans--History; Business enterprises--Virginia--Madison County.; Debt--Virginia--Madison County.; Divorce suits--Virginia--Madison County.; Estates (Law)--Virginia--Madison County.; Equity--Virginia--Madison County.; Free African Americans--Virginia--Madison County.; Land subdivision--Virginia--Madison County.
Geographical Names:
Madison County (Va.)--History; Madison County (Va.)--Genealogy
Genre and Form Terms:
Chancery causes--Virginia--Madison County.; Deeds--Virginia--Madison County.; Judicial records--Virginia--Madison County.; Land records--Virginia--Madison County.; Local government records--Virginia--Madison County.; Plats--Virginia--Madison County.; Wills--Virginia--Madison County.
Selected Suits of Interest
- 1803-003: Exrs. Of Robert Beverley vs. Mackenzie Beverley:
  Contains will of Robert Beverley, Sr., of Essex Co., builder of Blandfield Plantation. He Freed enslaved personal attendant and "his wife."
- 1818-002: Simon B. Chapman vs. John Wright, etc.:
  Suit concerns a contract for substitute militia service and discusses some generalities about the War of 1812.
- 1822-005: James P. Sims vs. William Jarrett, etc.:
  Suit initiated because Jarrett was accused of murder by coroner's inquest and flees county. By law, coroner takes possession of Jarrett's property and Sims sues to get title to land he paid Jarrett for.
- 1823-017: Mary Clark vs. William Davis, Asgn.:
  The suit references plaintiff boarding with defendant and raising several "young Negroes" for him.
- 1824-002: Jonathan Roberts for another vs. Daniel James:
  Depositions detail sale of a slave Dicey who was afflicted with cancerous tumors. Discusses assessment, treatment, etc.
- 1830-005: Joseph Good vs. J. B. Norton, etc.:
  Concerns a patent dispute over rights to improvements to Bergen's self-sharpening plow.
- 1837-007: Moses, a slave, etc. vs. Exr. of John Stockdell:
  Slaves sued because Stockdell's will called for them to be turned over to American Colonization Society for transport to Liberia (with funds from estate to pay for passage.) Executors have continued to rent out slaves even though there are no debts owed by estate. Judged in favor of plaintiffs.
- 1839-004: Joseph Hume vs. Exrs. Of Joseph Clark, etc.:
  suit contains genealogical chart and extensive explanation of familial relationships of whole and half-blood.
- 1844-008: Henry Hill vs. Humphrey Taylor:
  Parties in suit were slave traders who sold slaves in Mississippi nd Louisaina. The suit includes extensive slave lists with names of purchasers. Over 520 slave names listed.
- 1844-012: Exx. Of Mrs. Elizabeth Carter vs. May B. Bradford:
  Slaves freed in will, then some not freed in codicil. Mentions father of one of the slaves living in Richmond (with Mrs. Pilcher) and that he be consulted as to her placement when the time comes for her to be sold.
- 1844-014: Nathaniel Tatum, etc. vs. William H. Twyman, etc.:
  Suit involves slave traders.
- 1854-011: William J. Carpenter, etc. vs. Admr. of Thomas Shirley, etc:
  Suit concerns will of a woman under "fanatical influence of Shakers" who renounced her inheritance of a slave from Thomas Shirley.
- 1856-001: Exr. of John Thompson vs. Lucinda J. Thompson, widow, etc.:
  Will of Thompson calls for sale of slave Allice to settle debts. Allice recently had child and administrator asking to sell both together because the child is "of such tender age that humanity, justice, and regard to the true interest of the estate forbid the separation of the mother from the child."
- 1867-010: Jacob G. Weast, etc. vs. Admr. of Benjamin Burton, etc.:
  Plaintiff found substitute for defendant in CSA Army ca. 1861 and was promised 500 dollars in three payments. Collects one payment and defendant dies. Suing for remainder. Administrator contends that debt is invalid because it concerns service for the CSA, and the only true government of Virginia was the Restored Government (pro-Union) now back in place in Richmond. Argument fails; judge sides with plaintiff.
- 1870-012: David Beazley vs. Rosanna Beazley:
  Parties in suit are former slaves. Plaintiff explains that he and his wife cohabitated before the war, were emancipated by the war, and became lawful husband and wife through the Cohabitaion Act. Bill discusses living arrangements and sheds light on post-war situation for freed African Americans.
- 1882-005: Staunton Jackson vs. Sophia Jackson:
  Post-Civil War African American divorce suit that discusses a belief that five years of separation constituted a divorce, an "idea which has prevailed among the colored people." Also discusses wife's illegitimate mulatto children.
- 1883-002: Sarah T. Carpenter, etc. vs. John C. Utz, etc.:
  Suit mentions a slave insurrection.
- 1891-032: Exrs. of Charles Hume vs. Hannah Sparks, etc.:
  Suit concerns the settlement of Charles Hume's estate. Hume died in 1860 and provided in his will for "two old negroes" Charles and Hay (later referred to as Hay Taliaferro). Charles dies before or shortly after Hume. There is some question as to an agreement between Hay and Hume's executors regarding his care and maintenance. Hay, a petitioner to the suit, claims to have been duped by the executors into signing an agreement that was not to his benefit. A decree from the Supreme Court of Appeals in the suit seems to imply that Hay has no standing in the suit since he was freed at the end of the Civil War.
- 1906-019: M. B. Rosson vs. J. H. Robison, etc.:
  Rosson was partnered with Utz in "a hobby horse outfit" (merry-go-round)
- 1919-001: Adms. Of Thomas Shirley vs. Heirs of Thomas Shirley; Zachariah Shirley v. Adms. Of Thomas Shirley:
  Suit contains letterhead depicting a political cartoon relative to the 1844 Presidential race. Suit begins in 1840s and carries on to early 20th century. The suit deals with an estate. It contains extensive genealogical information as well slave family relationships and occupations